## Kiprop Amos | Data Scientist

+254 700093772 | Email | LinkedIn Profile | Github Profile | Kenya

#### **SUMMARY**

Ex-Analytical Chemist transitioning into a data science role after completing a data science certification program with a diverse experience of 2 years working collecting and analyzing essential oil data, creating SOPs, setting weekly production targets in a team of 5 that resulted in the long lasting impact in the organization. I'm currently looking for a role in Data Science.

#### SKILLS

- Data cleaning and preparation
- Data analysis and exploration
- Machine Learning using various regression and classification models
- Neural networks
- Building interactive dashboards using excel, Tableau and PowerBi
- Python and R (R Markdown) Programing languages
- Github
- SQL (MYSQL, Microsoft SSMS)
- Critical Thinking
- Innovativeness

## **Projects**

## Analyzing Kenya's 2022 elections using unsupervised learning | Link: Project Link

- The project aimed at predicting the winner of the presidential election, charting the popularity of various political parties and formations, and aspirants, and major topics being discussed in the run-up to the 2022 elections in Kenya.
- Tools: Python, Twitter API, Github, Streamlit, Figma, Canva for slide presentation, Jira

### Predicting house prices using machine learning | Link: Project Link

- The aim of the project was to use various regression models to predict house prices in New York and compare their performances
- Tools: Python, Github,

## **EXPERIENCE**

1. Part-time Kipsigis Contributor | Lugha Yangu

November 2022 - Present

## Roles and Responsibilities

I write on the culture, language, and organization of my community the Kipsigis community

# Work\_Sample

2. Biochemist | The Gallmann Memorial Foundation

Sept 2019 - Oct 2021 | Laikipia, Kenya

# Roles and Responsibilities;

- Maintenance of hygiene of distillation site
- Maintaining records and quality of essential oil distillations and leaf collection
- Experimenting on various techniques to recycle biomass used in distillation process
- Oversight of the distillation site, distillation boiler and processing area

- Processing of the raw essential oil
- Trialing different methods of extraction
- Trialing different raw botanicals
- Experimenting with different mixtures and ingredients for the creation of soaps creams, hair products and any other products as instructed by the directors

### **Key Accomplishments:**

• As the head biochemist, I headed tweaks in the distillations procedures that lead to an increase the essential oil yield by 10% while cutting distillation time by 6%

#### **EDUCATION**

## **Primo Academy** | Data Analytics Trainee Program

Expected Jan. 2023

 Courses - Introduction to Data Analysis with Excel, SQL and Python, Data Engineering with Big Data Technologies, Data Science and Machine Learning, Data Viz with PowerBI and Automation with Power Platforms

## Moringa School | Data Science

Graduated in July. 2022

- Courses Introduction to Data Analysis with R, SQL, and Python, Machine Learning, Data preparation processes, Data Visualization with tableau
- Link: Credential

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology |BSc. Analytical ChemistryGraduated in June. 2019

• First Class Honors

## Certificates

Certificate: Data Engineering Essentials | Issued by Coursera Authorized by IBM

Date: 07/2022 - 08/2022

**Date:** 18/12/2022

Link:Credential

**Certificate:** Data Analytics and Visualization Virtual Experience| Issued by Forage

• Link:Credential

# Volunteer Experience

- Chairman AVICO youth group: The group located in my home area is aimed at aiding youth acquire extra income by enganing in horticulural farming and rearing poultry.
- Vice Chairman Debate Club: I'm an opinionated individual who enjoys articulating topics I believe in through constructive debate.

#### Referees

Shall be availed upon request